Hi, I'm former CIA officer John Kiriakou
and you're watching the Break It Down
Show.
Yeah, I love I love what I get to do.
How many times have you you've been
interviewed by someone who's got
legitimate intel counter-intel chops?
Not a ton. Um
I'm going to say in the last five years
I could probably count it on
less than two hands.
Yeah. Why are we so afraid to talk out
loud to each other? And
like you see
I look at what we do, whether you're in
the Department of Defense, CI, wherever
you're at. This is a very specialized
job and even within that, you know how
this is. Like we're so
you know, we could probably count over a
hundred jobs in counter-intelligence
alone. We're not even talking about
SIGINT or anything else.
And it's so hard to know when someone's
good, so hard to know what direction to
go, so hard to develop yourself. Like
what books to read? I'm like all of
them. Read all of the books.
You know, a a great friend of mine, a
Bruce Fein, not just one of my closest
friends, but my attorney as well. He was
the Deputy Attorney General under
Reagan.
He he maintains a list of 100 books that
every American should read. And he's
really serious about this. Every
American needs to read these 100 books.
And I think he's absolutely right. And
to get back to your point that you made
just a second ago
why is it that we don't talk about these
issues? Why why is it that we're not out
there? You know, I I was on the Danny
Jones podcast, I'm going to say three or
four months ago and I debated a guy a
former agency guy named
Andrew Bustamante. And Andrew's got his
own following, he's a popular guy.
And
it ended up getting kind of explosive,
which was fun. It was all in good fun.
But we ended up, even though we came at
this from completely diametrically
opposed sides, we ended up agreeing on
like 80% of what we wanted.
Right.
You know, it's not like we're out to to
bash each other. It's not like we're out
to, you know, make a point at the
expense of somebody else. You can have
You can have a serious conversation with
another professional and you can
disagree like gentlemen while respecting
each other.
And that's missing from so many outlets.
It's just missing.
It's uh
I want to dig back into what you're
talking about and it's a great way to
We'll say just take all of the theory
out, all of the politics out. If you and
I were to go out and we're working
together as a team and I'm sitting in on
your meeting, I you know, my job is to
shut up.
Maybe I get to ask a question. Maybe I
send you a note, but I'm staying the
[__] out of your way.
There is nothing more uncomfortable than
being the guy who it's not your meeting.
You're just like, oh my god.
Yeah, cuz you're so dying to say
something.
I know, right? And and you know, that's
part of that is is
I Like if you and I were to sit down,
you know, we would get to know each
other real fast and be like, okay, good.
I trust you to do it and get done what
you're going to do and you're going to
trust me. But you like sailing and I
like boxing as an approach to getting
the answer. And and I'm like, what are
you doing?
Yes.
So hard to sit in and not do anything
other than be completely like
just Oh my gosh. And that's That goes to
the bigger thing of these conversations.
There's so many different ways to
approach this job.
So true. You just reminded me of
something. I I had no intention of
bringing up, but the last time I was in
Afghanistan,
I went with with John Kerry. I was the
chief investigator on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee and he was chairman
of the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee. So there were four of us all
went together and um
you know, when you go with a CODEL, it's
a congressional delegation, it's a big
deal. But when you go with the chairman
of the oversight committee, it's a very,
very big deal. So,
they they laid out this briefing. And
you know how military briefings are with
all the PowerPoints and the different
slides and decks.
So, we're all sitting around this this
conference room table, and it's 12
generals
from one star to four stars
and Kerry
and my boss, me, and then sort of an
assistant.
So,
they're doing an order of battle. I hate
order of battle briefings cuz they're so
incredibly boring to me, and they change
every 15 minutes, and they mean nothing.
So, they're saying, well, we've got
elements of the first platoon here and
elements of the third mountain division
there and we, you know, blah, blah,
blah.
We come out of that briefing, and Kerry
says,
now mind you, this is 10 years after the
start of the war.
Kerry says,
"We may actually win this thing."
And I said, "No, we're not going to win
this thing. This is the same briefing
that they've been giving for the last 10
years. I said, 'Hamid Karzai is the
mayor of Kabul. That's it. The Taliban's
got the rest of the country. We're not
going to win this thing. That's just
happy talk from the generals because
they know that you have the ability to
hold up their budget.' That's all this
was about. Oh my god."
It's
the amount that we lied to ourselves
without necessarily lying. It It's It's
amazing. You know, I I I got to stay in
the areas for a long time. I got to
learn how we were each iteration. So,
when we showed up, I'm like, I already
know what you guys are going to do. I
already know the mistakes you're going
to make. And all I can do, and this is
the intel guy talking, is try to get you
I I look at my job, tactical combat
collection, is is help the commander win
more, lose less, help the enemy lose
more, win less.
That's right.
And I I I understand like the mission
statements cuz they're all the same,
right? That's not a knock. That's just
how the machine works. And then you have
to mix in State Department or US Ag or
contractors for all these things. And so
I'm just looking at all of this and I'm
just trying to go to the top boss that I
can get to and be like,
"Here is the input that you guys are
putting in your staff meetings
everything else. Here's what they're
telling you what's happening."
And then I go out after all that stuff
and I talk to the locals and I say,
"Hey, what's going on here?" And they're
like, "These motherfuckers." And then
they're not talking about the things,
you know? And and you start to going
ahead of their decisions. So I'm like,
"Here's the status quo.
Here's the status quo and in between
there's all this [__] where we're not
being honest." And commanders who got it
got it right away and they started
slowing down their operations. Go.
You just reminded me of something else.
So I went to Afghanistan by myself in
2009, again with the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee. I wanted to do a
study a formal
committee uh research project on
um heroin poppy cultivation.
Mhm.
At the time, Afghanistan produced 93% of
the world's heroin. 93%
of the world's heroin. So I flew into
Bagram
God bless the guys at the Missouri
National Guard. They flew me from Dubai
to uh to Bagram directly.
And um
I got to Bagram. They said, "What do you
want to do?" I said, "I want to go to
Kandahar and Lashkar Gah and I want to
go into the poppy fields." They were
like, "Absolutely not." Well, it is not
my nature. It has never been my nature
to pull rank, ever.
Right.
And I said, "Look, with all due respect,
I'm a senior congressional staffer. I
outrank all of you. I have general
officer rank here. So with all due
respect, if I say we're going to to
Kandahar and Helmand, we're going to
Kandahar and Helmand."
Hour later, we get on a helicopter. We
go to Kandahar. They have, you know,
their briefing set up for me. Then we go
to to Helmand province to the the
village of Lashkar Gah. Now there was a
State Department outpost there.
Um that only had maybe a dozen people.
So it's in literally in the midst of the
poppy fields.
And these guys couldn't have been in any
more danger, right? So I get there and
they said, "Well, we have this briefing
set up." And I said, "No, I appreciate
it, but I want to get in a Jeep and I
want to go out into the poppy fields.
And I want to talk to poppy farmers."
They hated that idea.
But we got into the Jeep with a
translator and a security detail. We
went out, we find a poppy farmer.
So we drive up to him and we're talking.
And I said, I asked him this very naive
question.
I said, "Why do you grow poppy instead
of growing crops with two growing
seasons? Why don't Why don't you grow I
mean,
Why don't you grow onions or tomatoes or
pomegranates?" And he goes like this, he
goes,
"The Americans told me in 2001
that if I told them where the Arabs
were, I could grow all the poppy I
wanted."
There it is.
And I said,
"What American told you you could grow
poppy?"
And my handler's like, "Meeting over.
This is too dangerous." He physically
pulls me back into the Jeep. We go back
to Lashkar Gah. And then I fly back to
Bagram and then
God bless the guys from this time the
North Dakota National Guard, they send
me back to Dubai and back to Washington.
So I write this up.
Yep.
And I send it to Kerry.
And um
and he says, uh "No, we're we're not
going to we're not going to publish
this."
And I said, "Why not?"
And he said, "Look."
And in fact, I said, I said,
"Afghanistan produces 93 of percent of
the world's heroin.
And he said, "Almost all of that heroin
goes to Russia and Iran, and we want
them to be addicted to heroin.
It makes them weak. It weakens their
cultures and their societies, and we
want that heroin to go there."
So, I ended up publishing a paper that
was maybe 20%
of what it was supposed to have been.
Yeah.
And it's not really about heroin.
Yeah, I am not surprised to hear that.
And when I say this to you, you'll know
that I'm coming from a position of
respect for what you've done. When you
show up in that poppy field and talk to
that farmer, you are naive, right?
Yeah.
You need a guy like me. You need a guy
like me. And like when these generals
would show up, and they're like, "I can
see the future. I can see bizarre."
And they get their hands in the air, and
I'm like, "You are like a little child
out there."
You're a civilian.
You know what I'm talking about. We're
going to bring this harvest in. Like
I talked to an army major one time on
the I'm hard on the ag teams cuz look,
they deserve it. They want the job, you
[__] it up, here's the cost.
And they wanted to build these
collection centers, which is you know,
it's it's like a a roof with some sort
of shielding around the sides, and the
farmers were going to bring their wares
and put them down, and then the buyers
would come be like, "Oh my gosh."
Nobody's ever thought of creating a
market.
And so, um and then you know, so the
buyers and not buyers like customers,
but like, you know, the the mass buyers
Yes.
would be impressed, and then they would,
you know, sell more. They There's all
this whole thing. We would never ask the
governor where we should put this thing
if they wanted it in at all. We never
talked to the farmers.
And they would they would say, "Do they
understand? Do they understand what this
thing's for?" And I'm I'd say to the
major, I'm like,
"What What's the process? What's What's
market chain from farmer to Pakistan or
wherever these things go and they're in,
you know, somebody's house and they're
going to eat it. What what's that market
chain look like? Well, I don't know. And
I'm like, well, why are you [__] with
it?
You know, and
Yeah.
I had to write these things up and and
these guys had no idea. So, you know
what I do? I go out and talk to the
farmers and I'm like
That's it. That's what you have to do.
How does Yeah, how does the harvest
work? Tell me everything. I'm
fascinated. And they tell me everything.
And they had a system, it was
established and good change it if you
want to, America, but at least know that
it exists. And then you can decide if
you want to [__] with it. We hate that.
We hate that.
You know, I I went to Afghanistan as a
private citizen in 2007. I I had
consulted on a film called The Kite
Runner based on the book. Right.
Right.
And by Khaled Hosseini. And um
And I uh
I went to Afghanistan to get the child
actors out of the country.
And so, I had a I had a
free day and I had a bunch of friends in
the American Embassy both CIA and State
Department. So, I went over to the
Embassy. Hey, how you doing? We had
lunch and they just happened to have
this marketplace set up
across the street from the Embassy
where local Afghans came and sold, you
know, food or bread or
you know, souvenirs or coins or
whatever.
We had to take a tunnel
from the Embassy across the street
to the market because it was too
dangerous to cross the street
in a secure zone
surrounded by the American military. So,
I wrote this up as an op-ed for the Los
Angeles Times when I got when I got
back.
And um
The The LA Times entitled it The Other
War We're Losing
because everybody was so focused on Iraq
in 2007. They weren't really paying
attention to Afghanistan anymore. So,
they called it the other war we're
losing.
Then a couple of the days later, I get
an email from the editor.
And he says that they got an email from
OVP, the office of the vice president.
It was Dick Cheney at the time.
And I said
an email for me? From Dick Cheney?
They said, "Yeah, he wanted to comment
on the on the op-ed." I said, "What did
he say?"
All the email said was, "This guy's full
of shit."
Yeah.
"Thank you, Dick Cheney."
There's There's a
I'm not on a where it is, but there's a
line where no long like I call it the
spaceship. That's the best way to
describe it. It's like Star Trek. You
got all the people up in the spaceship,
and they're going to come down, and
they're going to fix the people's lives.
And And the
axiom I've come up with is
you cannot presume to improve the
condition of someone something that you
refuse to understand the condition of.
Yeah.
You know,
we import the problem, we import the
solution, and don't bother with the
results. You know, it's just like
Pete, I got to tell you, my my very best
friend from high school, um
joined the army as soon as we graduated.
It was he army reserve, but he he did
very well for himself, and he ended up
getting promoted to full bird colonel.
And he was stationed in Iraq as we used
to call him the garbage the garbage king
of Iraq because he was in charge of
solid waste disposal.
Right.
He actually died at 44,
from a a very rare brain cancer
that came from the burn pits that he was
in charge of. Yeah. But anyway,
I was at the CIA at the time. He was in
the military at the time stationed in
Iraq. And um
And he said something to me that was
just shocking. Cuz I've known this guy I
had known this guy all my life.
And he said, "You know, the only
solution here is we have to kill
everybody."
And I said, "What in God's name would
possess you
to say something like that?" And he
said, "Well,
they don't want freedom and democracy.
So, we have to force them."
And I I was like, "Dave,
what are you talking about?"
But, you know, that was the conventional
wisdom in the Pentagon at the time, and
at the CIA, and at the State Department,
and at the White House.
You know, the only people who who never
agreed with that, in my personal
experience, were the Joint Chiefs of
Staff.
They were the most reluctant
to commit big numbers to these to these
wars, and nobody paid any attention to
them.
Yeah.
There's a belief, and maybe it's
accurate, you know, that we shouldn't be
nation building. I would say state
building, cuz there's a difference
there, and it's more academically
driven, but
we never bothered with a license to come
in and do the thing that we wanted to
do. You know what I mean? I'm even weird
about language, and I and the way I
illustrate this usually is I talk to all
of my SEAL friends and all of my Green
Beret friends, and I'm like, "Have you
fired more rounds in combat in these
places, or conversations?" And they're
like, "Oh, it's conversations by far."
And I'm like, "Which one did you train
harder on?"
And they're like, "No, no, we don't
train at all to talk to people,
but we shoot a lot of rounds."
Absolutely right. Absolutely right.
So, we don't even know if we can do this
or not, right? And so, we make these
statements like, "We have to kill
everybody, cuz that is our hammer." And
we're like, "If we just kill more
people, we'll kill our way out of it."
And that's never the case.
Historically, that has never worked.
Never.
You can't kill your way out of it.
Yeah.
And the whole point is to win hearts and
minds. Um doing that with bullets isn't
going to work.
Here's a great one for you. When you
topple another government and try to put
one up, you are the insurgents. So, we
were the insurgents and we wanted the
hearts and minds for us. Commanders all
the time would say that. They're like,
don't don't think that way.
The governor needs the hearts and minds.
The governor is the boss. Stop being the
boss. Stop being the most influential
man in this valley.
Right.
slowly slowly would get But by the time
they figured that out and really started
to grasp it and really drove their unit
in the right direction, they had to
start boxing things up and and then the
next unit it wasn't that there were 20
in Okay, it is true that there were 20
individual wars over 20 years, but we
had complete amnesia that anybody else
had done this and we just
would not could not accept that this
problem I don't know how many times they
asked me, John, how many schools are in
that valley? And I'm like, why don't you
already know that?
You know, I'm going to find it out. And
by the way, I'm going to go ask the
Afghan or I'm going to go ask the shake
and they're going to tell me.
And I can do that all day long. You
should be asking harder questions by
now. And this is one of the reasons I'm
part of the on the GOs and everything.
You got You all are over your careers
because you couldn't handle the past 20
years.
Quite literally. Yes.
Yeah.
Yeah, you know, this is an ongoing
theme. And it doesn't matter who happens
to be in the White House.
It doesn't matter who is making the
decisions.
They're all the same.
Yeah.
This goes back to that Kerry thing about
let's enfeeble these people. I know that
we have a problem with opiates in our
country and have had for quite a while.
I know where those opiates come from,
too.
Yep.
So, when we look at these problems, we
make these statements like let's let's
you know, we've done this in Ukraine. We
do this in a lot of places where we pick
this like we'll
call we snap snap the chalk line.
Anybody on that side of the chalk line,
bad news.
Amen.
And and they're
When you talk to those people, they're
like,
I'm a vendor.
I don't care what you guys
do.
That's right.
What do you mean I'm a bad guy? I I, you
know, and or I'm a businessman and I
don't I never have done business with
the US cuz I don't care. That's not my
world. And and we'll decide at the
at the foreign policy class of people.
They they write these papers,
you know, like all the people that Look,
you know these guys. And and again, God
bless. Everybody's doing their best,
right? It's really hard things to figure
out. And like, this is how the Russian
war is going to go down. Put a PhD
behind my name. There you go. PhD. And
so, they're desperate for that always to
be the answer. They can never be wrong.
So true.
And then you go on the ground and talk
to people, it's nothing to do with what
they're talking about.
I've said many, many times in podcasts
that I've done that the day before we
invaded, the night before we invaded
Iraq, uh the senior director for Middle
Eastern Affairs at the National Security
Council said in a secure video
teleconference,
his exact words, "They're going to throw
flowers at us when we cross the border."
It's like, no, we're the occupiers.
We're invading their country and
occupying them. They're not going to
throw flowers at us. And certainly they
didn't.
Right. Yeah. And then we came and they
wanted us
Yeah, I know.
They wanted us to be great. You know, I
talked to a lot of Iraqis. You know,
like, it was so great.
We had our country back, and you guys
[__] it up.
Yes.
Yes. And now look what happened. Now
there's no Sunni bulwark against Iran.
Um Iraq is essentially a weak client
state of of Iran.
And uh and uh the the Gulf Arabs are
going to be forever in fear for their
safety.
If we looked at the
Yeah, no, we did that. And and
I took me a long time to learn this. So,
let's not act like Pete's omnipotent. I
had to talk to a lot of Iraqis. I had to
really like try to And I don't know that
I still grasp it cuz all these things
I'm not of that place, and so it's very
hard to get. But uh one guy taught me,
and basically he said is it's not
sectarian. This is not Nobody cares that
much about Muhammad around here. We're
pretty western if you guys would let us
be.
Yes.
He's like, the problem is and you guys
have a problem like this. This is like
whites and blacks.
And when you
can't solve that problem in your
country, you for sure can't solve that
problem in our country. And I was like,
"Oh [__] he's right. He's right."
Got that right. That is absolutely true.
We just don't get I can't tell you
how many times I had to speak at little
classes being held at um
at the the Pentagon or the State
Department to try to explain to people
in the most basic terms the difference
between a Sunni Muslim and a Shia
Muslim.
Yeah.
And that there are different varieties
of Shias depending on where they are.
Are they from Oman or from Yemen or from
Syria or from Iraq?
And
people just
their eyes glaze over and it just goes
over their heads. Like it just doesn't
make any sense to them. I I was in
Kuwait. I went into Kuwait in 1991. In
In February of 1991, I went to Kuwait
with the Marines on Liberation Day.
And there was a general there.
He wasn't the commanding general
in Kuwait. He was like the deputy.
And um
the Kuwaitis have this tradition of
something called the diwaniya. So it's a
it's like a political discussion group
for men. And so they have these these
big living rooms set up in their houses
that they called uh
diwans. Or
it translates to salon. And men will
come over one night a week. Everybody's
got their diwaniya on a different night.
Come over, you drink tea, you drink
coffee, you eat little cookies, and you
talk politics. And it's it's a
free-flowing thing.
So this general says to me,
"When are you going to take me one of to
one of those diwaniyas.
And I said, "Oh, a diwaniya?" I said,
"Yeah, I'd love to take you to
diwaniya." I said, "Actually, tonight I
was going to go to one that's being
hosted by the Kuwaiti ambassador to
Mauritania, who was kind of a
kind of a character in Kuwaiti politics.
So, we go to the diwaniya.
Uh and uh
you're supposed to take off your shoes
when you walk in, just out of
good manners.
Not only did he not take off his shoes,
but he was wearing obviously combat
boots.
And then when we sat down, they gave the
general the the seat of honor next to
the host.
The general puts his combat boot up on
the coffee table. Listen, there is
nothing more offensive in Arab culture
than to show the sole of your foot
because
the sole of your foot is where you step
into [__] outside. Right? So, it's
considered exceedingly bad manners to
expose the sole of your foot.
And his foot I kept whispering to him,
"General, put your foot down. General,
put your foot down. You can't put your
foot up there, General."
Afterwards,
Mohammad Kadiri, the the ambassador, he
said to me,
"Please don't ever bring that man to my
house again."
Right.
It's like talk about how to win friends
and influence people. Like, dude, all
you had to do was 5 seconds of cultural
sensitivity.
Yeah.
To not offend everybody in that room.
And that's the basics that you owe to
have that license to go over
cross-culturally. I
Yes.
you know,
if you
were to handle that in a different way
and say, "Hey, you know, my uniform
requires that I keep my boots on. What
do you guys think about that?"
Exactly right, Pete.
You know.
Exactly right. Now, you've just
liberated their country three or four
days earlier, and they're going to say,
"Oh my god, by all means keep your keep
your boots on. We totally understand.
God bless
I am the standard bearer, right? My guys
see me without my shoes on, I go, "Now
listen, you guys tell me, do I should I
take them off or not?" And they'll be
like, "Cuz I did this, right?" And so I
I would say, "Hey, um we're all eating,
we're on the floor eating with our
hands." And I said, "You know, this is
an interesting thing. You guys know I'm
from California. Um I eat with my left
hand, but I'm told that you guys don't
like that."
There you go.
And they go, "Pete,
you're from California. You're not in
Iraq. Eat with whatever hand you want.
We're just glad to be your host." And I
was like, see and I when I did these
things, I would do these a lot with my
interpreter. I'd say, "I'm going to ask
questions and say things that you know I
know, but I'm doing that for a different
reason." And oftentimes just to show my
partners, you know, in on the American
side. And again, I'm not omnipotent. I
[__] all these things up. But when I
go out into an area, if they're not
wearing kit and gear and helmets, all my
stuff comes off. It'll stay next to me
on the ground cuz I've got to keep track
of it.
That's a very important point. And you
know, when we first crossed into Iraq in
2003, um and moved into Basra, that's
exactly what we did. All the gear came
off. Even the helmets came off when we
first approached the
the leaders in Basra, both both civic
and religious, everything came off. They
put their hands over their hearts. Oh,
thank you for liberating us. We see why
you're here. Everything is great. And
then little by little, and mostly it was
cuz we were so jumpy about our own
security,
all that gear went back on and then we
looked like occupiers.
Right.
Once we looked like occupiers, we were
treated like occupiers.
I'm going to put a picture up here. This
is me
talking to a bunch of sheikhs.
Awesome.
see right behind me, my gear is on the
ground.
I I do.
Awesome.
I'm talking directly across, not my
interpreter, but the guy just off his
right, that guy is dead. Sheikh Case,
right? He lived in a place where his
involvement politically was dangerous
and would ultimately kill him within a
year of that of that photo.
And
you know, it was dangerous, but these
guys do live in that life and they do
not wear gear, right? Cuz they have a
different uniform. You've seen Sheikhs
and how they kind of float around the
room when they have that shake walk and
everything.
Oh, yes.
We have to understand that if we're if
we presume to go in somewhere and
improve that place, we have to know the
Sheikh cases of the world and understand
that how they got to where they got to
is a path that we need to understand
before we start offering different next
steps for them cuz they have a different
world than us.
You know, that that was especially true
in Afghanistan.
In in 2001, starting around November or
December of 2001,
where we had for all intents and
purposes, we had destroyed Al-Qaeda. Um
we had killed many of them. The rest
were just pushed out into Pakistan. So
in terms of Al-Qaeda in Afghanistan, we
had destroyed them. So then George Bush
George W. Bush used that god-awful word
nation-building.
Well,
Afghanistan had a 3,000-year-old
tradition
of um
of something called the Loya Jirga.
The Loya Loya Jirga was a committee of
Sheikhs
who
ran the place.
Right? If you had a dispute with your
neighbor, you would go to the Loya
Jirga, you'd argue your sides of the
issue, they would make a decision.
It was their form of democracy.
Well, we didn't like their form of
democracy. We liked our form of
democracy, and so we imposed it on them.
This is a country that had literally
zero experience with Western-style
democracy, but we thought we were
smarter than they were,
we knew better than they did, and so
damn it, they're going to use our way or
it's going to be the highway.
And 20 years later,
we bug out and the Taliban uh comes back
to power. And I I want to say one other
thing about the Taliban.
This is something that we never
understood, and I mean, White House,
State Department, and DOD under
presidents of both parties.
What we didn't understand was that the
Taliban
did not descend from the moon and just
float down and impose themselves on
Afghan society. These are the husbands,
the fathers, the brothers, the sons
of Afghans.
Mhm.
And so, whether we like it or not,
whether we understand it or not,
they would rather have the Taliban
than have us.
And so, we had no business being there.
Yeah.
And if you're going to have business
being in there, understand that that
barrier is in front of you.
That's right.
And we didn't understand it.
Right. Right. When When you talk about
jirgas, and I'll say the word shura as
well. These are both meetings of a kind,
and we would say, "Oh, well, you have to
go to the education shura." You know,
and they would tell the Afghans how to
run their lives.
Yeah.
And again, it took me a long time to
figure this out, but a shura is not a
shura, a jirga is not a jirga unless
there's holy men there, because it turns
out most of the world doesn't separate
government and religion. And so, we hate
that. And we like like uh
you you have General Order Number One,
it's like, "Pete, you got to stay out of
them mosques. You don't you dare go in a
mosque. If I get invited to a mosque,
guess where I'm going."
I went.
I'm going to go right on in.
I've lost I've lost count of the number
of mosques I've been to.
Yeah. One of the mosques I went to
wasn't even a mosque. It was a pad of
dirt. That That's where they That's what
the mosque was there. And And I stood
there, and I didn't do that I didn't ape
being Islamic, and they call that, as
you know.
But I was someone's guest while he
prayed, you know? And so every day I'd
go to prayer with him. And I was in a
mosque every day, right? Yeah, and
because we're afraid of the the culture,
because we don't want to offend, we
don't ever get to leverage this to our
advantage. And so when we go to these
meetings that we gen up and call the
shura, they're like, "Yeah, sure. I'll
go to the shura." But um guess who's not
there? The Taliban. The the holy men are
not there. And when you see those guys,
when you go to a meeting that's not
driven by Americans, and you see them
actually
make community decisions, yeah, there
are Taliban members there. And they go,
"Yeah, cool. That's part of the deal. We
can do that." But where I worked, and
this is just for everybody, I know you
know this, but I worked in the area
where a guy named Mullah Omar was from,
and he was living there in his house,
and we never caught him. A mile from all
our close
we didn't even know he died until 6
years afterwards.
I'm true. I was there when he was still
alive, you know? You think my god,
Pete's a great spy. He could have find
it out. I could I had no clue. But I
also wasn't looking for him. I was
trying to understand
when we were like, you know, just leave
the Taliban. And I'm like, "Dude, that
guy's brother is in the Taliban." You
know, of course he's tied to it. Doesn't
mean he's a bad guy. Doesn't mean his
Taliban brother's a bad guy. But they
are they are of this place. You can't
wipe them out. You can't ignore them. No
one's going to trust you who's not going
to stay.
Well, this is where they're from. And
people people couldn't accept or
understand that the Taliban is part of
that community.
And and I'll add this next piece and
then I'm going to shut up and let you
go, but there's a guy at every PRT and
and he gets to wear civilian clothes.
He's in the military. And his job is to
run the "Hey, Taliban, come in from the
cold. We'll give you a package of goods
and aid, and we'll get you back on the
right path." That guy is in every
province, and that guy can go there for
a year, 6 months, whatever it is, and
convert zero people and get a high five.
"Good job." And no one ever goes, the
[__] we doing?
A buddy of mine from the State
Department
wrote a book about it and it was
entitled how I helped to lose the hearts
and minds of the Iraqi people.
Yeah.
But it's not the only book written like
that.
No.
Now, you're absolutely right.
It's um uh
I'm thinking about Peter um what's his
last name? I know him because we were in
the same area. Anyhow, he was Oh, this
is very much
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. That's him. That's him.
Yeah. I I I'll think of his name when I
think about it.
Department whistleblower.
Uh
Right. Just like you, he's like, "Hey,
this isn't working."
And
just like you, they're like, "You know
how you had that retirement and all
these other things? Actually, we we
think we want to throw you in jail
instead."
Yep. There it goes.
You know?
Yeah.
There it goes.
And he just barely And then the And the
No, uh the ACLU came and fought for him
because of what he did, right?
He was the
ACLU.
It was the ACLU and it was the
Government Accountability Project, GAP,
whistleblowers.org.
And
Yeah.
they they ended up having to go to court
and he was that rare victory.
Uh but Hillary Clinton personally tried
to ruin his life.
Yes.
Right. Mhm. Peter Van Buren was his
Peter Van Buren, thank you.
Yes. Yeah.
Yeah.
So, he and I worked in the same part
Actually,
Wow.
Peter Van Buren
uh
Bradley Manning at the time and myself
all sat within maybe 25 circular feet of
each other in three different offices,
but no no difference at all, all at the
same time, right?
god. Bradley Manning, now Chelsea
Manning, got arrested day before
yesterday.
Oh, no.
Protesting in front of the Speaker of
the House's office.
Well,
you know.
I don't know. I don't know what to do.
You know,
Peter and I both had this conversation
about what we would have done if and
again, I'm using in the tense of the
time, if Bradley Manning would have sat
one of us down, which happened for me
all the time. Yeah, soldier be like,
"Hey Peter, I want to talk to you. Go
let's go have lunch." Or let's have
midnight chow.
If Bradley Manning would have sat down
with me and said, "Hey, I have this
thing. I have this information."
You know, and I would have said, "You
have to report to superior chain of
command." And if he's like, "I don't
think I can." I don't know what I would
have told him. I don't know what I would
have told him.
I can tell you from my own experience
what I would have done differently.
I blew the whistle on the CIA's torture
program. And my situation was unusual in
that I couldn't go through the chain of
command because my chain of command
created the torture program.
Right.
Um
I would say go to the oversight
committees. Now, in my case,
the oversight committees approved the
torture program and funded the torture
program. So, I was stuck there, too. But
I think I think Manning should have gone
to the um to the House and Senate Armed
Services Committee.
She would have gotten some
some measure of satisfaction, I think,
doing that. Uh I ended up going to the
media. Manning went to WikiLeaks, and
then the rest is history.
But those oversight committees, for
better or for worse, are there for a
reason. And um
that should probably be the first step.
If I was sitting down
with PFC Manning at the time. And again,
to ask a PFC to go stand in front of an
oversight committee.
Yeah, that's that's a bridge too far.
Right. But um I I at one point was in
Bosnia um during the the main push,
right? During '96. And I end up getting
no pay due. No pay due, everybody, is is
when it's the monthly payday and no
money comes in. And I got no pay due.
And it was a problem. Something had
gotten screwed up. And so, I said
heard of that before.
Yeah. Yeah. And it's it's procedural,
right? And no commander wants to see a
soldier get a no pay due. Looks bad on
them. And so I went to my commander,
shoulder shrug. And I'm like, all right,
why I have to fix this? And again, I'm a
specialist. I don't know how to fix
these things. And so I go to the IG. And
the IG um says, okay, great. Look into
this, but also call like your upper
level personnel people and see if they
can tell you what's wrong. And they had
turned me into a divorced Mexican lady.
And I'm like, wait, hold on. I'm not
that. You know? And And so like, well,
okay, obviously you're not a lady. And
obviously you're you're not a a Mexican
lady. You're you're this guy Pete. Okay,
so we see a problem here, but
how can you prove you're not divorced?
And I'm like, how do you prove I am
divorced? You know? So
I filed this IG complaint and they came
back and it was like, nah, no problem.
And I'm like, what do you mean no
problem? You know? And so when you have
that, when you've done that thing
before, and if I'm sitting with PFC
Manning,
I'm like, I wouldn't trust anybody
internally. That's what exactly what I
probably would have said. I think
because how could you? If If I couldn't
I couldn't have anybody prove externally
that I wasn't If I didn't fix this
myself E4,
um I would have kept getting no pay dues
and they would have said I was a Mexican
lady with a divorce. It sounds crazy as
I say that. I'm like, it's like I'm
making it up, but it absolutely
happened.
That just makes me It makes my brain
want to explode.
Yeah. Yeah. And how can you be an IG,
which is the Inspector General
everybody? These people look into things
like this and they go, here's what's
going on.
And And look, I'm not saying all
Inspector Generals are bad, but how do
you When they When one element
compromises your integrity,
But you know what? The The DOD Inspector
General actually has a reputation for
being among the worst Inspectors General
in government. And And I'll add too that
the IG at the CIA is literally the only
bright spot at the CIA.
The The IG is literally the only person
in the CIA that you can trust. It's the
opposite at the Pentagon. Do you know Do
you know Tom Drake, the NSA
whistleblower Tom Drake?
No, I don't. Uh-huh.
Oh, Tom Tom's got a story, man. Tom's
Tom was an Air Force uh
an Air Force colonel. And um his very
first day on the job at NSA
uh as a civilian in the Senior
Intelligence Service, his very first day
was September 11th, 2001.
Wow.
And so
the attacks take place and uh General
Mike Hayden, who at the time was the
head of NSA, later became the head of
the CIA,
decided to implement
um a collection program called um
uh Thin Thread.
Uh Thin Thread
just vacuumed up all communications from
all Americans.
Emails, phone calls, text messages,
voicemails, everything.
Well, they had also developed a second
uh
technology called Stellar Wind.
Right.
And Stellar Wind
used AI to discern what was a potential
threat and what wasn't.
And so
Tom said, "Hey, you know, this this Thin
Thread, this is this is wrong. This is a
mistake. It's a violation of law. We
can't collect data from American
citizens or from US persons. That's an
American citizen or anybody in the
United States on a green card." He was
told to mind his own business.
So, he did exactly what you're supposed
to do. He went through the chain of
command. He went to his boss, who told
him, "Keep your big mouth shut."
Yeah.
Mind you, he's been on the job for a
day.
Then he went to the Inspector General.
Well, the Inspector General wasn't read
into the compartment. So, the Inspector
General didn't know what in the world he
was talking about.
Right.
Then he went to the General Counsel. The
General Counsel said, "Buddy, this is
way over your pay grade. You need to
stop.
So then he gathered all the information
that he could on paper and he went to
the Pentagon Inspector General.
The Pentagon Inspector General
reported him to the FBI
and then destroyed the evidence that he
brought out.
Then he goes to the Congressional
Oversight Committee. He goes to the the
uh sorry, the House Permanent Select
Committee on Intelligence and reports,
you know, I think I've stumbled on a
crime being committed by NSA. What
happens?
The FBI raids his house,
takes all of his electronics, which he
has never gotten back.
Mhm.
And they arrest him and charge him with
nine felonies
including seven counts of espionage
and two counts of theft of government
property. The government property being
the information that he walked out of
the building with in his head.
Yeah.
They offered him a deal.
20 years. Do 20 years in prison on an
espionage charge. He told them to go
[__] themselves. Now, he was broke
because they they also confiscated his
uh bank accounts. So he had a public
defender.
The night before the trial,
the entire case fell apart and they
dismissed all the charges.
Yeah.
But Tom spent the rest of his career
working
at the Genius Bar at the Apple Store
in Bethesda, Maryland.
They took his pension. They took his
security clearance. They uh they
described him as an insider threat,
which he was not, of course. And his
wife, who was also an NSA employee, left
him.
Yeah.
That's what they do.
They do. They do. They do exactly that.
And they do it And they is it's a lot
it's a lot of theys out there. Um
there's a guy named Richard Caruso who
worked in the prison system. You know,
it's big 6'4 former Marine. He was the
first guy through the door when they had
to go knock heads with you know, an
inmate.
Yeah.
And his prison, Corcoran in California,
was the deadliest prison in the nation.
Right. And he was the one that said no
more. But he had to and this goes back
to Chelsea Manning's, you know, benefit.
He had to smuggle out evidence over a
long period of time. And he had to
record every phone call. Because not
only did California turn you know, not
only did his peers turn on him, but
California state turned on him. And then
the FBI turned on him. All of them
trying to put him in jail. And he always
had the receipts and he had a badass
lawyer and that lawyer is like ching
that's going to cost you money. Should I
play the tape now or you just want to
shut up? And they'd be like, no, play
the tape. And he's like, k- k- k-
And so they paid him a lot of money
because but only because he knew like
because he had some investigation
background and he knew just to
constantly record everything they said.
You know, they would put up these bogus
investigations against him and
everything and and then they would go
away and they would say, well, there was
that investigation and he was like, and
it was bogus and it was disproven and I
have the file for that. I know you
probably can't find it, but luckily I
have a copy.
And these things happen. Man, they
happen all the time. You know, and
All the time.
It's
It and we don't realize how badly it
destroys lives.
Yeah, you're exactly right.
You're exactly right. There's there's no
end in sight and nobody learns a lesson
from these things. You know, it just
happens over and over and over again.
It's precious when people like want to
come after somebody's clearance and
livelihood and then you look and and
look and this is not political. So you
just look at all of the
compromising things that happened in
Congress and and in the executive
branch, you know, where we know Donald
Trump broke the law. We know that Joe
Biden broke the law. It was a
classification. We know that a secretary
Clinton broke the law. We know that all
these things happened.
But nobody held her accountable. Dianne
Feinstein had a Chinese spy on her chief
of staff in California. No problem. Adam
Schiff constantly leaked classified. No
problem. So,
they all and if Here's the things. Guys
on our side of the table, if we worked
for an adversarial country, I'd bet get
me to DC cuz I'm going to run some
sources. Yeah, I'm going to make my
career because they don't they won't
hold themselves accountable.
And I can find the guys
who are like you or like Van Buren or
whoever. I can find those guys and I
know what to do with them and I can turn
that into my advantage.
Let let me if if I may. I want to read
to you the short text of a of an email
that I received on Saturday. This is the
third third time this has happened in
the last 10 years.
Okay.
Dear John, it's nice to finally speak
with you. I've been watching your
YouTube interviews and I love all the
content and I've been wanting to reach
out to you for many years. I'm one of
the FBI agents who would like to
personally apologize to you for the
disgraceful way the FBI and our
government treated you. I worked with
both the headquarters and the Washington
field office teams on your case and I
know many of the personnel that you're
familiar with. That case was directed
and driven by senior officials. It was a
political case. Many mid-level and
street personnel were against it but
nevertheless, we followed orders.
Anyway, I've always felt bad about what
I did and for you and the way you were
treated and I wanted to personally
apologize to you. Sincerely and then he
signs it.
Yeah.
Third time in the last 10 years.
Right. And there are good people that
will, you know, try to do the right
thing but anybody anybody can get
swamped. Like when you get your position
working with Carrie, there's only so
much you can do. Right? You want to do
way more. And there's only so much he
can do.
And so like if you find yourself and you
don't these boundaries are not visible
to you.
Find out when it's like
So you've gone past it.
Oh, listen. I I was doing a I was doing
a study for Carrie and and so I wrote a
letter to the CIA under Carrie's
signature asking for clarification on on
a on a classified issue.
And a colleague of mine like 6 weeks
passed. A colleague of mine comes into
my office and he said
Oh hey, I saw the agency responded to
your your inquiry.
I said I didn't see a response. I just
checked my my mail an hour ago. And he
said oh, they classified it top secret.
So it's in the vault.
And I said well, what did it say?
And he said it says go [__] yourself.
And I said okay, that's how they want to
play it.
Yeah, it's it is how how it works. I
want to I'm going to put a link up here
for this
First of all, before I do that, let's
put a link up here because I want to
support what you're doing and everybody
If you guys are enjoying this, John's
Substack is packed full of things. I'm
going to be subscribing as soon as we
get off air. I'm going to put a link up
here. Just
Thanks, Pete.
Yeah. Because we need to have these
voices, your voice, my voice because the
other option is you get the Afghan War
Commission from the United States
Senate, which I sent my I sent my resume
to. I've emailed all of the important
people and said hey, I'd love to
understand more, love to be involved in
some way. You don't have to hire me,
right? But I've got a lot of expertise
in my head. I've done the stuff at the
ground level. There's no way they have
enough of that. And every person that
they've hired
is an academic. God bless. Love our
academics. You don't have any dudes that
have a thousand combat patrols talking
to a local so we can They will not talk
So
I have no respect for the commission
just because they don't understand that
that is more of the problem. They're not
going to get to anywhere. And then
what's anybody going to do anyhow? Like
we have a center for lessons learned and
all of those
It makes you laugh.
A stinger for lessons learned.
Come on.
Yeah.
Like the CIA, this woman I sat next to
for years, she said to me one day, I'm
transferring.
And I said, oh, what are you
transferring to? And she says, I'm going
to the center on Nazi war crimes.
And I said,
is there such a thing?
And she said, yeah. I said, but
the CIA wasn't even created until 1947.
And she said, yeah, I know, but there's
still some documents that need to be
declassified. I'm like, what?
Okay. All right.
It's like the center for lessons
learned. Okay.
Yeah.
Knock yourselves out.
It's It's uh
when I tell people I Look, my friend
came back from Afghanistan, he was doing
some private work out there.
And he's really knowledgeable.
And he got a little too high up, I
guess, and he said to me, you know, I
don't know how long the government's
going to last, you know, maybe 6 months,
2 years, something like that. I'm like,
no, John, it's gone. It's There's no
government. Those guys all are going to
about-face the second that we leave,
because there's no reason to stay alive
if if you don't. And he's like, no,
it'll last a little longer than that.
I'm like, I don't know what you're
reading,
but I saw these guys. They were
terrified to be where they were. They
had no provision So, so, I'm going to
tell you this little story, and I know
you'll appreciate this. So, again, I'm
an intel guy. I'm looking wherever the
intel is, wherever I can help the
commander win more. So, uh we get into
this firefight, and it's the Afghan
police, and you know, our little
contingent, but mostly the Afghan
police, and they fire a bunch of [__]
off and everything. So, I go to the
chief of police. He's the young guy. And
I cuz we're in the For everybody
listening, we're in the middle of
nowhere. You can't picture how desolate
this place is.
Right.
And I said to him, hey, what are you
going to do to re-provision your your
people? And he's like, oh, it's no big
deal. I just um send something up a
request up, and they'll, you know,
pretty soon they'll they'll send um ammo
back to us, right? Cuz these guys don't
have a giant store. These guys live in
mud houses. They have nothing.
Oh, yeah.
And and money was already a problem.
Getting these guys paid reliably and and
even sorting out what was true, what was
not. So, I I followed the request to to
take up our chain that goes up their
chain as well. Same request.
And I you know, I don't have to do this
every day cuz you have to let the
process work and I've got other things
to do. But if I went back into the main
part of town, I would ask, "Hey, where's
that thing?" "Oh, yeah, I sent it over
to so-and-so." In this case, it was a
sergeant first class in the army. And
he's like, "Yeah, I killed that
request." And I'm like, "You killed that
request? Oh, that guy's a bad guy. He's
tied to the Taliban." And I'm like,
"What the [__] are we living in Zabul?
Everybody's from the Taliban."
Everybody's really everybody. Every man
over the age of 14 is in the Taliban.
Yeah. Yeah. There's no way to Like you
can't not Oh, is the government going to
work or not? Cuz it's not even your
call, dude. I mean, okay, sure, maybe
position in the army. But there's an
actual guy that just got into a
firefight with the Taliban. I I
I was there, you know? Like I I know.
And couldn't It didn't bother him. He
didn't even have a second to think about
the fact that his
complete ignorance as to like what's
going on when you're
maybe 40 miles away from where he was
sitting. Just complete unawareness of
that,
you know, denied the government the
ability to do what the government needed
to do to to create at least with the
dudes within the government some
connection.
Right. Right. And still, they just don't
learn the lesson. It happens over and
over again.
Yeah. We'll do the same things in
Ukraine once we get a calm down. We're
going to take people that have energy
erupting out of the ground. We're going
to be like, "You guys need green
energy."
Yeah.
You know? And
Exactly.
we're going to take
I learned quite a bit about Ukraine
because of this. Um I was working on a
project and the people that know how to
build big, powerful industrial
businesses, those are all called
oligarchs, you see.
Yeah. Exactly. We only use that word for
Russians and Ukrainians. We don't call
Jeff Bezos an oligarch.
No, he owns a media company. Well,
that's different.
Right, democracy dies in darkness.
Yeah, I mean it's we're laughing cuz
it's it's patently ridiculous.
It is.
It's absurd.
anything we can do about this? I mean,
look, you take your crack and look what
happens.
Yeah, they smack you right down.
Yeah.
You know, I
My my ex-wife once criticized me saying
that I never saw a bridge I didn't want
to burn. Uh but the truth is, I figure I
I might as well just go out there with
my opinion and and appear on on podcasts
and shows and talk to guys like you
where we can have a a mature informed
conversation
and hope that maybe we get people out
there to thinking. And maybe that
translates into electing more
responsible, better informed uh public
officials. I mean, you know, it's a it's
a long-term it's a long-term project.
Yeah, I I've got a nonprofit that I'm
trying to start, you know, and it's like
you only have so many hours in a year to
put into something like that when it's
not funded and everything else. And I
got people wanting to like give me
money, but they're like, "Hey, I've got
to figure out how do I" So, all these
things can only move at the pace they
move at, but it's exactly this where
you're going to go into Congress and
you're like, "Hey, I need to find
somebody who knows this stuff from the
ground point of view." Even if it's not
that specific conflict, guys like you
and I can say, "Ooh, slow down right
here."
That's just too much.
indeed.
Right. And get that expertise in house.
And And by the way, it's not just
combat. So, I I was talking to you, do
you remember the the show Little House
on the Prairie?
Sure.
And then the girl that played Nellie
Olson, her name is Allison. And she was
on the front line cuz she's a Hollywood
girl, right? So, she's on the front
lines of the AIDS epidemic back in the
olden days.
And here's like the mighty lefty, you
know, I'm from California so I can make
I can talk [__] about California.
Um
But here they are like we know how to
fix the AIDS epidemic. We're going to
put out flyers that say don't have
male-to-male sex unprotected. You know,
she's like that.
Yeah, exactly. We made flyers, right?
And and people think oh that's not what
they do. Guess what? You go all around
the government. Their way communicating
is putting out a flyer that sits right
there in their lobby and anybody can
have it and they never get rid of them.
So that's
I went to see Abbie Hoffman speak when I
was in college. I saw Abbie Hoffman
speak at George Washington University.
It was in the midst of the just say no
campaign. You remember this? Just say no
to drugs. It was Nancy Reagan's thing.
And he said how preposterous it was that
telling telling a drug addict to just
say no is like telling a
manic-depressive to just cheer up. It
doesn't work. It just doesn't work.
Yeah. And and and so you know like this
whole ground truth institute thing it is
about that. It's about getting an
Allison to say uh how about we start at
a different step, you know, like let's
get to know some of these guys. And you
know, look case management is hard. I'm
sorry. It's going to be hard. Fixing a
country that's broken and full of
criminals and and crime and death and
destruction, it's just not going to be
easy. You're going to have to say the
whole thing that I was saying about
instability is instability like we are a
net destabilizer. When we show up [__]
gets broken even worse and everybody
except for us is good at instability.
And we want these stable machines to
work all the time and inexorably go up
the screen and to the to prosperity, you
know, that's the arrow. But everything's
a cloud and as soon as you try to grab a
cloud you're like why did I do that? You
know, you never get the cloud.
So true.
So true. I couldn't agree more.
Yeah. It's it's uh
It's great to talk to someone who gets
this at this level.
We know here's the thing I struggle with
is we know so many smart people,
well-intentioned people,
well-read, well-written,
But for whatever reason, they don't have
the ability one to hear someone like I
always say it like our first mistake is
not realizing that that we're making the
first mistake. Like we just we cannot
seem to wrap our heads around. Why is
that? Why do we have these incredible
people, hyper talented, who can't seem
to I'm going to use a story to
accentuate this. I had I was working
just south of Sadr City and I had a guy
a rocky guy who going to Sadr City tell
me all about it. So I happen to be the
main palace
and talking to this PhD guy that that
kind of worked in my organization. And
he was like, "I'm writing a paper on
Sadr City." I'm like, "Oh, you're in
luck. I've got a guy inside there who
can tell you whatever." He's like, "Oh,
I don't need that."
These guys, how do we
How do we treat these guys? How do we
figure out what to do with them?
I I can tell you from the CIA
perspective that the problem is one of
group think.
Um
In fact, I'll give you an example. It's
a little bit dated, but in order to get
my uh promotion to GS-15, I needed to
write a national intelligence estimate,
an NIE.
And uh so the national intelligence
officer asked me to write one of these.
And what a national intelligence
estimate is for people who don't know
the term is it's a paper
that is coordinated by every single
intelligence agency in the American
government. So it is the opinion of the
entire intelligence community.
So the NIO, the national intelligence
officer said he wanted this paper to be
called Iraq: Saddam's
next 12 months.
This is back in 1997.
And so
I said without getting into details,
Saddam could
uh threaten the Kurds, he could threaten
the Shia, he could threaten Kuwait, and
he could interfere with the weapons
inspectors.
So,
the NIO calls him a coordination meeting
and it's members of all 18 intelligence
agencies in the American government.
It's chaired by the NIO.
And what you do is
he reads aloud the first sentence.
What does everybody think about the
first sentence? DIA, what do you think?
Department of the Air Force, what do you
think? Department of Energy, what do you
think? Okay, then when that's all
settled, you read the next sentence.
Okay, so sometimes these things take
weeks to coordinate.
Mine took 4 hours.
And at the end of it, yeah, at the end
of it, he said to me, "That is the
fastest coordination session I have ever
participated in. Congratulations." And I
said, "Ben, I said, "I'm ashamed of this
paper."
All we needed to do was take last year's
NIE and change the date. We didn't say
anything new. Nobody had any
outside-the-box thinking or analysis. I
said, "I'm ashamed of this thing."
But that's the curse
of of intelligence, especially
intelligence analysis.
You're just not going to get people who
are willing to risk
their next promotion, their hallway
reputation by going on a limb and
saying, "You know,
I think Bashar al-Assad may be
overthrown in the next couple of days."
You know, nobody's going to say that.
No. When I When I worked in the I worked
in the DOD for part of my time and we
had to write up our annual review and to
see if we could get a bonus. Everybody
like you can get a bonus in in these
government departments. And so they
always kind of figure out like how to
work these programs. And so I had to
justify what I'd done. And so scale of
the one to five, nobody gets a one and
basically nobody gets a five. And when
you do get a five, it's like you've
changed the industry. Like it does
things different. That's sort of the
standard. And I'm like, "Well, I'm doing
things that are like five level. I'm
going to claim a five until they say no.
But like, yeah, well, you'll never get
it. I'm like, oh, okay, great. So, I
spent hours writing this thing cuz
that's what you're supposed to do. And
build the government a lot of money.
And then my boss has to read it. And and
then talk to me and then revise and then
read it. And so, I would say this
process took
75 hours
of my of my time, right? Pulls me off
the battlefield, but I've got to do it.
And they come back and and here's what I
had done during this time. I got a
brigade sergeant major. Brigade is 5,000
people.
And he said, Pete, you came in for us.
Well, actually, we I got to them. But
he's like, you came in to us and we
didn't know who you were and you had
said that you were going to help us
correct our mistakes before we start to
make them.
And you did that. I didn't believe you.
And now, within a very short amount of
time, you and your buddy Rich have
turned this entire brigade 180° to get
us going a different direction. And we
couldn't have done it without you.
I didn't ask for that.
Right? And they're like, yeah, Pete, my
my organization, yeah, not that
impressed. You get a three. Middle of
the road, $1,200 bonus or whatever it
was. And and I'm like, yeah, see, this
is the thing is I already got more money
by writing this stupid thing cuz I
didn't trust anybody in my organization,
but
Good thinking.
We were
we were changing things in a positive
way that saves all of us money, saves
all, you know,
and it was enormously successful on the
intel side.
And you couldn't get people in the
institution to see something different.
People did get fives. They all work
right by the flagpole and they were all
connected in a way. And I'm not saying
anything bad about them. Maybe they did
incredible things, but I can't believe
they changed how that part of the
industry worked. And that's part of our
problem is is we have these entrenched
people
that
that can't have a field guy come in and
say, "Hold on, ground truth is going to
matter here." You know, I'm going to
give you another story then I'm going to
shut up and let you wrap it and then
we'll be done. But we have these
aerostats and we think that all you got
to do is throw it up there and you can
see everything and it's cool. It's great
and I'm like, yeah, but
people don't understand people on the
ground don't understand what that is.
And so they get to invent whatever
reality they want from it. And one of
the realities I've uncovered is that my
buddy built it this, is they thought it
had x-ray vision and could see their
wives naked bodies and they hated it.
Right? And you tell it to a commander
like, "What doesn't do that?" I'm like,
"It doesn't matter if it doesn't. It
doesn't matter."
it does it.
Yeah.
Oh my god.
Oh, you know, I'll tell you one thing. I
was part of an analytic unit.
Um
I had this personal rule that if you met
with a source
and you did not come out with an
intelligence report, you failed.
Yeah.
Okay, you're going to a lot of trouble.
There's a lot of work, a lot of time,
and a lot of danger
in meeting with a clandestine source.
So, if you come out of there without
having anything to write, you have
failed.
So,
there was 1 month where this unit of six
of us wrote 54 intelligence reports. I
wrote 36 of those 54.
And I thought, man, I'm going to get
promoted so fast, I'm going to get a
bonus.
I got a call from my boss.
And he was a little bit mad.
And he said, "You need to slow down and
back off."
I said, "What are you talking about? I'm
like kicking my own butt here to be
productive." He said, "You're making
everybody else look bad and it's pissing
people off."
Yeah.
"Okay." So, you know what I started
doing? In the middle of the work day,
I would go to the gym for an hour.
Yeah.
Yeah. And you know, you got to get
changed, you got to take a shower. So,
my hour at the gym was really 2 hours.
So, instead of working my 8-hour day,
I'm working a 6-hour day. I slowed down
a little bit.
And then that made them happy. And
another thing, I had a boss, my very
first boss. I used to get You could set
your watch to when I would get to the
office every single day at 6:00 a.m.
Right.
And my boss, the big boss, my boss's
boss, would saunter in at 9:00 for his
9:30 meeting.
Well, the work day was 8:00 to 4:30. I'm
in there at 6:00. So, I was working 6:00
to 4:30. Well, he would come in at 9:00
and then he would wander around at 5:00
to see who was still at the office.
So, he told my immediate supervisor,
"Hey, there's a problem with Kiriakou.
He's a clock watcher. He's always out of
here at 4:00."
Well, I'm in 3 hours before he is.
Right.
So, my I said, "But I I'm working I'm
working 10 and 1/2 hour days."
Yeah.
rather than 8 and 1/2 hours.
And he says,
"You're going to have to stay till till
5:00 till he walks around." And I said,
"Fine."
So, instead of going in every day in at
6:00, I started going in every day at
8:00.
So, I was working an hour and a half a
day less.
Yeah.
And I got the thumbs up.
It's uh it's crazy. It's
I mean, these things can happen.
That's That's government.
It is.
I would purposely cuz I I I knew how to
do my job and a lot of people I was with
had not deployed like I have. You know,
I I've just I've got a lot of time. And
so, I would figure out where the command
needed me. I would compel my team to let
me go. Sometimes these things got me
fired and kicked out of country. But,
you know, look, I've got to work the way
I work.
And so, then I would say like, "I'm
going to kick all of your asses in terms
of production and not like quantity of a
quality. I'm going to have better
products. I'm going to be enmeshed with
the command." My goal was if the
commander, battalion, brigade, whatever
it is, they didn't know everybody had to
know me best. Pete, Pete, hey, Pete was
here. I had to build a read This is all
my own demand on myself. I had to build
a reading list for my reports. I had to
go follow up, make sure these guys were
going to get caught unaware by not
reading my reports.
Cuz I would look, I would find things
out that mattered, you know? And the
commander would look around and be like,
he's kicking your And this is this is in
the unit, not even my team. My team
would become irrelevant. So, the
commander's like, Pete, wherever I go,
you're going to go. If you want to go
anywhere in the battlefield, you say the
word. If I want to go to poppy field,
guess where we'd go. Cuz I'd be like,
this is going to matter. And I would
give them information no one else could
give them, right?
Yeah.
And and then my headquarters way back
way back in the United States are like,
hey, uh you're working over 100 hours a
week. Oh, that's not possible. And I'm
like, you
Yeah, actually it is.
Yeah. Yeah, that that was my whole
existence in Pakistan. I had I made so
much overtime overtime, post
differential, danger pay, and language
differential, and per diem, I came home
and bought a house.
Yeah, right. Yeah.
Yeah. Oh, oh, you can work 100 hours a
week. It's no fun, but when it has to be
done, you do it.
And when you're in Pakistan or in
Afghanistan, whatever, you have to do
that. It's the only time to be there,
and no one else look, no one else in
that area is better than you or me at
going out and finding gold. You know, we
know what the standard is. You're 100%
right. Like, if you can't bring
something back valuable, then you
shouldn't be on that mission. And I was
hardly doing it.
Exactly. Exactly.
Yeah. It's all about the mission.
Listen, this has been a great
conversation, and I don't want to keep
you any longer. Uh we'll have to do this
again.
The pleasure's all mine, Pete. This was
fun.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Uh anything you want
to say in closing? Otherwise, everybody
make sure you go to the Substack. The uh
link is down there.
Uh thank you. I I put literally
everything I do on Substack. So, if you
want to have some fun, check it out
there.
All right, there we go. Stand by. I'll
be right back to you. And I'll say
goodbye to everybody else. See you
tomorrow.
Hey, thanks for watching the show. I
really appreciate it. Right here, you
can subscribe. Please do that. It makes
the show grow. Hit that notification
bell so you know which incredible guest
is coming up next. Down below is the
PayPal link. You can put a small
subscription in. That is an enormous
help. All that money goes right back
into the show. And then right up over
here are the next episodes you should
listen to, curated by yours truly. Thank
you so